Thomas and Jane Welsh Carlyle Photographs, late 19th century
Mortimer Rare Book Room
Thomas and Jane Welsh Carlyle photographs
1854-early 1900s
1870-1900
Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881
286
1 box (3 linear inches)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
Scottish writer and historian Thomas Carlyle and his wife, Jane Welsh Carlyle. Consists of photographs by Thomas of his wife Jane (some with his handwritten coments) and of Thomas Carlyle. There are also photographs by John Patrick of Edinburgh of sites and residences associated with the Carlyles. There is one holograph letter (1870) by Thomas Carlyle.
Thomas Carlyle (December 4, 1795-February 5, 1881) was a Scottish writer and historian and widely influential on Victorian life and thought. He married Jane Welsh on October 17, 1826.
Jane Baillie Welsh (July 14, 1801-April 21, 1866) was the daughter of Dr. John Welsh and Grace Billie Welsh of Haddington, Scotland, where her father practiced medicine. Haddington is southeast of Edinburgh.
The marriage between Thomas Carlyle and Jane Welsh was a difficult one, although with her death he went into deep depression. In their married life they lived in various places in Scotland and on Cheyne Row, Chelsea, in London.
John Patrick (1830-1923) was a Scottish baker turned photographer. After maintaining photography studios in various towns in Scotland, he opened a shop in Edinburgh in May 1884 at 5 Coniston Road. Eventually his sons joined him in this enterprise. He first photographed Thomas Carlyle in 1874.
The Thomas and Jane Welsh Carlyle Photographs consist of photographs of Thomas' wife Jane Welsh Carlyle; three of them have his handwritten comments on the photographs. In addition, there are numerous photographs by John Patrick of Edinburgh of sites and residences associated with the Carlyles. There also is one holograph letter (1870) by Thomas Carlyle concerning an image to be reproduced in one of his books; this letter, although purchased with the photographs in this collection, is unrelated to them.
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
The Thomas and Jane Welsh Carlyle photographs are a gift from the estate of Henry L. Seaver, 1976. Seaver acquired this collection from Walter A. Benjamin Autographs in New York City, paying $30.00, according to an invoice dated February 13, 1946 (in the Mortimer Rare Book Room office files).
Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881; Carlyle, Jane Welsh, 1801-1866; Carlyle, Jane Welsh, 1801-1866; Patrick, John, 1830-1923; Tait, Robert Scott, 1816?-1897
- Letter, 1870 May or Aug. 9 Chelsea to "Dear Sir" from T. Carlyle 1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  1 leaf.
  Thomas Carlyle writes concerning the reproduction of a mezzotint of James Nayler to appear in Carlyle's Cromwell's Letters and Speeches.
- Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyle [1855 Apr?] 1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  1 photograph mounted on board. Albumen print
  Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyle seated at a table, with her elbow on the table and her head resting in her hand. There are three books on the table, and the dog Nero is lying on the table. Inscription by Thomas Carlyle on the board: "Very like! (tho' peculiar & rare)". The National Portrait Gallery, London, attributes a photograph of Jane Carlyle, wearing the same dress and seated at the same table, to Robert Scott Tait, and dates the image April 1855.
- Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyle [1855 Apr?] 1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyle seated at a table, with her elbow on a book on the table and her head resting in her hand (slightly different pose than folder 2 above). There is also a small sculpture on the table. Inscription by Thomas Carlyle on the board: "Like, tho' slightly unfavourable (these 2)". The National Portrait Gallery, London, attributes this photograph of Jane Carlyle to Robert Scott Tait, and dates the image April 1855.
- Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyle undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  1 photograph on thin paper (possibly a proof). Albumen print
  Jane Welsh Carlyle seated on an arm chair, her elbow on the arm of the chair and her hand against her face. Inscribed on verso by Thomas Carlyle: "A miserable caricature; not one feature like, or even recognizable, pale, ah!-T. C. (Decr 187?)"
- Photographs of Jane Welsh Carlyle [1855 Apr?] 1855 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Albumen prints
  4 photographs mounted on boards of the same pose of Jane Welsh Carlyle in folder 3 above. The four photographs vary in tone and contrast. The National Portrait Gallery, London, attributes this photograph of Jane Carlyle to Robert Scott Tait, and dates the image April 1855.
- Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyle [1854?] 1854? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Jane Welsh Carlyle seated on a chair with a dog in her lap and a bonnet on her head. This image appeared in New Letters and Memorials of Jane Welsh Carlyle (London: John Lance, 1903. vol.2), titled "Mrs. Carlyle and Nero." It was reproduced from the photograph by Robert Scott Tait, 1854.
- Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyle [1854 Jul 28?]1854 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Jane Welsh Carlyle seated on a chair at a table, wearing a shawl, with her elbow on the table and her hand touching her face. She is wearing the same dress and is seated in the same chair as the photograph in folder 6 above. Copies of this photograph from Columbia University Library and Edinburgh University Library are attributed online to Robert Scott Tait and dated July 28, 1854.
- Photograph of Jane Welsh Carlyleundated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  2 photographs mounted on boards. Albumen prints
  Jane Welsh Carlyle, wearing a bonnet, standing with hands resting on the back of a chair and a dog on the seat of the chair; a dog is on the seat of the chair. Two different exposures.
- Photograph of Thomas Carlyleundated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Written beneath image: "From a daguerreotype 1848, T. Carlyle." Embossed at the foot of mounting board: J. Patrick & Sons, 52. Comiston Road, Edinburgh.
- Photograph of Thomas Carlyleundated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  1 photograph attached to a modern piece of paper. Albumen print
  Carlyle, with a full beard, seated wearing a cape. A similar photograph of Carlyle wearing the same cape, seated on a chair and with his head resting on his hand, is attributed in Wikipedia, to Elliot and Fry dated ca. 1860s.
- Photograph of Thomas Carlyleundated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  1 photograph, on thin paper, possibly a proof. Albumen print
  Carlyle seated, with his elbow on a table and his hand on a cane. There is a hat on the table.
- Postcard of Thomas Carlyleundated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  1 postcard.
  C. W. Faulkner & Co., London, E. C. Series no. 66A. The image of Carlyle (seated on a chair, resting his hands on a cane) is a reproduction of a painting (1877) of Carlyle by Sir John Everett Millais. The painting is now in the National Portrait Gallery, London.
- Photograph. "1226. Birth-room of Thomas Carlyle. Ecclefechan. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photograph. "1237. The Hill. Dumfries. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photograph. "1270. The Cairn Heights. Craigen Puttock. House hid among the trees. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photograph. "1238. The kitchen. Craigen Puttock. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photograph. "1237. T. Carlyle's study. Craigen Puttock. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographs in folders 18-24 can be dated as no earlier than 1895
  1895 was the year that the Carlyles' home at 24 Cheyne Row (5 Cheyne Row when the Carlyles lived there) opened as a museum (note the presence of exhibition cases in the photographs)
- Photograph. "1262. Cheyne Row, Chelsea. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Photograph. "1255. Drawing room. 24 Cheyne Row, Chelsea. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photograph. "1256. Drawing Room. 24 Cheyne Row, East End. Chelsea. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Photograph. "1257. Carlyle's attic study. 24 Cheyne Row, Chelsea. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Photograph. "1258. Carlyle's attic study. 24 Cheyne Row, Chelsea. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Photograph. "1259. Front and back dining-room, 24 Cheyne Row, J. Patrick." (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Photograph. "1260. Back dining-room, 24 Cheyne Row, J. Patrick." (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Photograph. "1253. Carlyle statue on the … J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Titling badly faded. This 1882 statue of Carlyle by Boehm in now in the Chelsea Embankment Garden, near Carlyle's house on Cheyne Row.
- Photograph. "1231. Thomas Carlyle's grave (in center). Ecclefechan. J. Patrick" (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Photograph of Thomas Carlyle's tombstone. (Box 1, Folder 27)